Finding Aid for Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records, 1956-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Deputy Vice-Provost for Information Technology 1982-1991
  - 1990-1991
    - Academic Affairs Advisory Council (AAAC) (Box 45)
    - All-Schools (Box 45)
    - Ann Arbor, City of (Box 45)
    - ANS (Advanced Network Services) (Box 45)
    - Apple (Box 45)
    - Architecture and Urban Planning (Box 45)
    - Business (Box 45)
    - CAEN (Computer Aided Engineering Network) (Box 45)
    - CICNet (Committee on Institutional Cooperation Network) (Box 45)
    - Confer (Box 45)
    - Consortium for International Earth Science Information Network (CIESIN) (Box 45)
    - Consulting and Support Services (CSS) (Box 45)
    - Correspondence (Box 45)
    - Customers (Box 45)
    - Cuts (Box 45)
    - Dentistry, School of (Box 45)
    - Development Office (Box 45)
    - Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC) (Box 45)
    - Diversity (Box 45)
    - Duderstadt, Jim (Box 45)
    - Education, School of (Box 46)
    - EECS (College of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science) (Box 46)
    - Engineering (Box 46)
    - Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) (Box 46)
    - Equity (Box 46)
    - Ethics (Box 46)
    - Executive Computing Committee (ECC) (Box 46)
    - Executive Information Systems (EIS) (Box 46)
    - Federal Government (Box 46)
    - Financial Aid (Box 46)
    - Ford Motor Company (Box 46)
    - Graduate School (Box 46)
    - Grievances, 1 folders (Box 52)
    - Guests / Visitors (Box 46)
    - Gulf, Persian (Box 46)
    - High Schools (Box 46)
    - Housing (Box 46)
    - IBM, 2 folders (Box 46)
    - IFS (Institutional File System), 2 folders; 4 folders (Box 46)
    - Information Services (IS) (Box 47)
    - Information Technology Access Fee (ITAC) (Box 47)
    - Information Technology Division Central (Box 47)
    - Information Technology Division Priority Services Review, Consulting and Support Services (CSS) (Box 47)
    - Information Technology Division RIF Procedures (Box 47)
    - Information Technology General Council (ITGC) (Box 47)
    - Information Technology Networking, Health Services (ITN, formerly ISHIS), 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Information Technology Policy Council (ITPC), 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Information Technology University of Michigan (ITUM) (Box 47)
    - Inside ITD (Box 47)
    - Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR) (Box 47)
    - Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) (Box 47)
    - Law School (Box 47)
    - Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) (Box 47)
    - Los Alamos Laboratory (Box 47)
    - Mail (E-Mail) (Box 47)
    - Marketing (Box 47)
    - Medical, Nursing Schools (Box 47)
    - Merit Computer Network and MichNet (Box 47)
    - Microsoft (Box 47)
    - Mid-Managers (Box 47)
    - Music (Box 47)
    - Networking and Fiber, 3 folders (Box 47)
    - Networking (Local Area Networks / LAN) (Box 48)
    - Network Systems (Box 48)
    - Network Systems Search, 1 folders (Box 52)
    - Newsletter (Box 48)
    - NEXT, Inc. (Box 48)
    - Northern Telecom, Inc., 2 folders (Box 48)
    - NSF Panel / Proposals (includes National Center for Supercomputing Applications programs) (Box 48)
    - NREN (National Research and Education Network) (Box 48)
    - On-Call Time (Box 48)
    - Open Software Foundation (OSF) (Box 48)
    - Oracle (Box 48)
    - Parties (Box 48)
    - Performance Reviews, 1 folder> (Box 52)
    - Personal Computer Sales (Box 48)
    - Personnel, 1 folders (Box 52)
    - Pharmacy (Box 48)
    - Plant (Box 48)
    - Public Health (Box 48)
    - Public Sites (Box 48)
    - Referring Physician’s Network (RPN) (Box 48)
    - Regents (Box 48)
    - Research (GIS, Remote Sensing, Imaging) (Box 48)
    - Research Systems (RS) (Box 48)
    - Residential Computing (Box 48)
    - SACUA (Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs) (Box 48)
    - Salary Program, 2 folders (Box 48)
    - Security (Box 48)
    - SILS (School of Information and Library Science) (Box 48)
    - Site / Software Licenses (Box 48)
    - SNC (School of Natural Resources) (Box 49)
    - Social Work (Box 49)
    - Space (Box 49)
    - Spires (Box 49)
    - Strategic Plan (Box 49)
    - Stats (Box 49)
    - SUN (Box 49)
    - Think About It (Values and Ethics) (Box 49)
    - Total Quality Management Council (Box 49)
    - UBC (University of British Columbia) (Box 49)
    - UM Background (Box 49)
    - UMTel, 2 folders (Box 49)
    - University Information Systems (UIS) (Box 49)
    - University Microfilms International (UMI) (Box 49)
    - UNIX (Box 49)
    - Vendors, Misc. (Box 49)
    - Video (Box 49)
    - Virus (Box 49)
    - Visualization Lab (Box 49)
    - Working Groups (Box 49)
    - Workstation Sales (Box 49)
    - Xerox (Box 49)
- Vice-Provost for Information Technology Files
  The Vice-Provost for Information Technology series (2.5 linear ft.) contains material from Van Houweling’s office for 1992 to 1995. It includes planning documents, committee files and notes, and records that complement and continue documentation held in the Central Files and other previous series.
  - 1992-1995
    - AAU (Association of American Universities) 1995 (Box 49)
    - Advanced Information Technology 1994-1995 (Box 49)
    - Ameritech 1994 (Box 49)
    - Ann Arbor Public Schools 1994 (Box 49)
    - AT&T 1994 (Box 49)
    - Banyan 1993 (Box 49)
    - Bellcore 1993 (Box 49)
    - Bell Data Network 1993 (Box 49)
    - Budget 1995 (Box 49)
    - Budget Priorities Committee 1992 (Box 49)
    - CENTEL 1992 (Box 49)
    - Center for Technology Integration (CITI) 1993-1994 (Box 49)
    - Central Committees 1993 (Box 49)
    - Chief Operating Officer 1993-1994 (Box 49)
    - Communications Forum 1994 (Box 49)
    - Computer Aided Education and Training Initiative (CAETI) 1994 (Box 49)
    - Computer Kick-Off 1993-1994 (Box 49)
    - Corporation for Public Broadcasting 1993 (Box 49)
    - Correspondences 1994 (Box 49)
    - Council on Competitiveness 1993-1994 (Box 49)
    - CREN (Corporation for Research and Educational Networking) 1993-1994 (Box 49)
    - Digital Equipment Corporation 1994 (Box 49)
    - Diversity 1993-1994 (Box 50)
    - Electric Society 1994 (Box 50)
    - Executive Computing Committee 1994 (Box 50)
    - Feedback on ITD Forum 1993 (Box 50)
    - Fraunhofer U.S.A. 1994 (Box 50)
    - Future Computing Environment (FCE) Project 1994 (Box 50)
    - Goals and Objectives 1994 (Box 50)
    - HEIR Alliance 1992-1993 (Box 50)
    - IAT 1994 (Box 50)
    - IBM / UM Steering Committee 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 50)
    - Information Technology General Council (ITGC) 1993-1994 (Box 50)
    - Information Technology Policy Committee (ITPC) 1994, 6 folders (Box 50)
    - Information Technology Security Education and Coordinated University Response Project (IT-SECUR) 1994 (Box 50)
    - Integrated Technology Instructional Center Executive Committee (ITIC) (became Media Union),1993-1995 (Box 50)
    - Internet (Public Access to) 1993-1994 (Box 50)
    - Kindergarten-12th Grade (K-12) (Box 50)
    - Library/School of Library and Information Science/ITD 1993 (Box 50)
    - Literature, Science & the Arts (LS&A) 1992 (Box 50)
    - MCI 1993 (Box 50)
    - Merit Computer Network 1994 (Box 50)
    - Microsoft 1993 (Box 50)
    - M-Link 1993 (Box 50)
    - M-Quality 1994 (Box 50)
    - Michigan Online 1994 (Box 50)
    - MTS (Michigan Terminal System) 1992 (Box 50)
    - National Bank of Detroit 1994 (Box 50)
    - National Information Infrastructure 1994-1995 (Box 50)
    - NREN (National Research and Education Network) 1993 (Box 50)
    - NS (Network Systems) 1993-1995 (Box 51)
    - NSF (National Science Foundation) 1994-1995 (Box 51)
    - NT (Northern Telecom) 1993 (Box 51)
    - Office of Instructional Technology (OIS) 1994 (Box 51)
    - Operations Lead Team (OLT) 1994, 1 folders (Box 51)
    - Orientation 1993-1994 (Box 51)
    - Policies 1992-1994 (Box 51)
    - Privacy 1994 (Box 51)
    - Satin Project 1994 (Box 51)
    - Science Development Council 1992 (Box 51)
    - Senior Management Agenda 1993 (Box 51)
    - Strategic Data Planning 1993-1994 (Box 51)
    - Strategic Lead Team 1994-1995 (Box 51)
    - Summit Networking 1992 (Box 51)
    - Taligent 1994 (Box 51)
    - TCI 1993 (Box 51)
    - Total Quality Management 1992-1994 (Box 51)
    - UMTV (Lynn Conway Project) 1993 (Box 51)
    - University Information Systems 1994 (Box 51)
    - University Strategic Partner Program (Box 51)
    - User Services Status Report 1993-1994 (Box 51)
    - Work Planning Information 1994 (Box 51)
- Virginia Rezmierski Files
  The Virginia Rezmierski Files, accessioned in 2000, are mainly for the period from 1987 to 1997. Rezmierski held the positions of assistant to the vice provost for policy studies and assistant to the vice provost for information technology. The papers reflect her role in coordinating information technology policy initiatives starting with the reorganization of the Computing Policy Committee in 1987. The series includes documentation on the Information Technology General Council and Information Technology Policy Committee. The series is comprised of four subseries: Administrative Files, Information Technology General Council (ITGC), Information Technology Policy Committee (ITPC), Information Technology Security Education and Coordinated University Response Committee (ITSECUR).
  - Administrative Files
    The Administrative Files (.50 linear feet, 1985-1992), while slight, contains some important background documents on the transition from the Computing Center to the Information Technology Division and from mainframe to distributed computing. Of particular interest is the report User Requirements for Implementation of Michigan’s Computing Transition from an MTS Centered Computing Environment to a Future Distributed Computing Environment and the materials relating to the Information Technology Architecture Committee (ITAC).
    - Budget Materials 1990-1991 (Box 53)
    - Budget Request 1990-1991 (Box 53)
    - Computing Policy Committee
      - Meeting Minutes and Related Documents 1985-1987 (Box 53)
      - Recommendations Report August 1, 1988 (Box 53)
    - Departmental Planning Team (DPT) 1988 (Box 53)
    - Executive Computing Committee, Agenda and Associated Materials February 7, 1989 (Box 53)
    - Information Gateway Project September 12, 1994 (Box 53)
    - Information Technology Architecture Committee (ITAC) (Box 53)
    - Strategic Factors and Future Directions September 1987 (Box 53)
    - Meeting Minutes and Related Documents 1987 (Box 53)
    - Information Technology Policy Committee/Executive Computing Committee, Relationships Draft Report 1994-1995 Network and Router Pricing, 1993-1994 (Box 53)
    - Reports
      - Administrative Technology at the University of Michigan: Plans for Tomorrow, July 1992 (Box 53)
      - Enhancing Quality in an Era of Resource Constraints, March 1990 (Box 53)
      - Guiding Principles for the Transition from Present MTS Computing Environment to a Future Distributed Computing Environment June 4, 1992 (Box 53)
      - Meeting the Campus Networking Challenge, not dated (Box 53)
      - Statement of Direction August 12, 1992 (Box 53)
      - Support for Information Technology by the University of Michigan Computing Center, May 17, 1988 (Box 53)
      - User Requirements for Implementation of Michigan’s Computing Transition from an MTS Centered Computing Environment to a Future Distributed Computing Environment, January 25, 1993 (Box 53)
    - Working Group for Academic Information Technology April 1992 (Box 53)
    - Senior Management Retreat Notes
      - 1986-1987 (Box 53)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 53)
    - Senior Management Retreat Presentation February 1991 (Box 53)
    - Services Review 1991 (Box 53)
    - Strategic Planning Discussion 1988 and not dated (Box 53)
    - Strategic Planning Document (Drafts and Revisions) September 1986 (Box 53)
    - Strategic Planning Materials December 1986 (Box 53)
    - User Services Needs Assessment Review September 15, 1987 (Box 53)
  - Information Technology General Council (ITGC)
    Information Technology General Council (ITGC) (.25 linear feet, 1987-1990) was one of the two committees formed in 1987 following the reorganization of the Computing Policy Committee. The main function of the ITGC was to serve as the principal mechanism for information exchange and communication. Committee members were elected for one-year terms and included representatives from the academic and administrative units as well as student representation. The series in this subgroup is limited in size and consists mainly of meeting agenda material for 1990.
    - Budget Materials 1990 (Box 53)
    - Clipboard, 1989 (Box 53)
    - Council Charge and Organization 1987-1988 (Box 53)
    - Departmental Planning Team 1988 (Box 53)
    - Glossary of Network Terminology June 6, 1988 (Box 53)
    - Information for Exchange 1987-1988 (Box 53)
    - Information Technology Division Organizational Chart May 11, 1988 (Box 53)
    - Meeting Agenda and Related Materials February 1990 (Box 53)
    - Meeting Agenda Potentials 1989 (Box 53)
    - Meeting Evaluations 1988 (Box 53)
    - Meeting Prep for Doug October 1990 (Box 53)
    - Meeting Survey and Evaluations 1989 (Box 53)
    - Membership Lists and Issues 1989-1990 (Box 53)
    - Membership Mailing List October 1, 1992 (Box 53)
    - Planning Team 1990 (Box 53)
    - Primary Staff Team May 12, 1988 (Box 54)
    - Small Group Summaries 1988 (Box 54)
    - Tour Sites circa 1988 (Box 54)
    - Transfer of Management of ITGC 1990 (Box 54)
    - Writing Team Council 1988 (Box 54)
  - Information Technology Policy Committee (ITPC)
    The series Information Technology Policy Committee (ITPC) (3.5 linear feet, 1983-1997), represents the largest and most complete series in the subgroup. With the reorganization of the Computing Center Committee in 1987, the ITPC was the second newly formed policy committee (along with the Information Technology General Council). The main function of the nine-member ITPC was to serve as a high-level advisory group. Membership on this committee was through nomination by the vice provost for information technology. Membership length was three-year renewable terms with rotating expiration dates. The series contains the charge to the committee and meeting agendas and minutes spanning from January 1988 through July 1997. Meeting minutes are arranged by date of meeting and documentation includes Rezmierzki’s hand-written notes as well as print-outs of electronic communications she had with individual committee members. The series nicely reflects Rezmierski’s organization and planning skills in documentation on priority setting, agenda planning, meeting evaluations and summary of action items.
    - Charge to Committee 1983-1984 (Box 54)
    - Charge to Special Committee 1993 (Box 54)
    - Computing Policy Committee, Report prepared by the Ad Hoc Committee on CPC Reorganization May 12, 1987 (Box 54)
    - Correspondence 1988-1990 (Box 54)
    - Demo File 1991-1992 (Box 54)
    - Executive Meeting Summary 1992-1993 (Box 54)
    - First-Year Evaluations 1989 (Box 54)
    - Meeting Agenda Planning 1995-1997 (Box 54)
    - Meeting Minutes and Related Documents
      - 1988
        - January 25 (Box 54)
        - February 18 (Box 54)
        - March 18 (Box 54)
        - April 15 (Box 54)
        - May 20 (Box 54)
        - June 17 (Box 54)
        - July 15 (Box 54)
        - August 26 (Box 54)
        - September 23 (Box 54)
        - November 11 (Box 54)
        - December 9 (Box 54)
        - October 14 (Box 54)
      - 1989
        - January 13 (Box 54)
        - February 10 (Box 54)
        - March 16 (Box 54)
        - April 14 (Box 54)
        - May 12 (Box 54)
        - June 16 (Box 54)
        - July 14 (Box 54)
        - September 11 (Box 54)
        - September 22 (Box 54)
        - October 13 (Box 54)
        - November 10 (Box 54)
        - December 8 (Box 54)
      - 1990
        - January 12 (Box 54)
        - February 23 (Box 55)
        - March 29 (Box 55)
        - April 27 (Box 55)
        - May 25 (Box 55)
        - October 26 (Box 55)
      - 1991
        - January 11 (Box 55)
        - February 12 (Box 55)
        - March 12 (Box 55)
        - April 9 (Box 55)
        - June 24 (Box 55)
        - July 24 (Box 55)
        - August 20 (Box 55)
        - September 17 (Box 55)
        - October 8 (Box 55)
        - November 12 (Box 55)
        - December 10 (Box 55)
      - 1992
        - February 18 (Box 55)
        - March 17 (Box 55)
        - April 21 (Box 55)
        - May 26 (Box 55)
        - June 23 (Box 55)
        - September 22 (Box 55)
        - November 11 (Box 55)
      - 1993
        - January 13 (Box 55)
        - February 3 (Box 55)
        - March 10 (Box 55)
        - May 12 (Box 55)
        - June 16 (Box 55)
        - November 23 (Box 55)
      - 1994
        - January 18 (Box 55)
        - March 23 (Box 55)
        - May 25 (Box 55)
        - July 20 (Box 56)
        - September 7 (Box 56)
        - September 21 (Box 56)
      - 1995
        - January 29 (Box 56)
        - February 7 (Box 56)
        - February 13 (Box 56)
        - March 24 (Box 56)
        - April 25 (Box 56)
        - May 11 (Box 56)
        - June 21 (Box 56)
        - September 18 (Box 56)
        - November 8 (Box 56)
      - 1996
        - January 29 (Box 56)
        - March 27 (Box 56)
        - June 20 (Box 56)
      - 1997
        - March 6 (Box 56)
        - March 23 (Box 56)
        - May 28 (Box 56)
        - July 29 (Box 56)
    - Membership List 1988-1990 (Box 56)
    - Membership Notes 1990-1991 (Box 56)
    - Notes 1987-1990 (Box 56)
    - Policy Drafting 1988-1989 (Box 56)
    - Priority Setting 1990-1991 (Box 56)
    - Reports
      - Advancing Educational Uses of Information Technology at the University of Michigan September 10, 1987 (Box 56)
      - Considerations and Recommendations Concerning Administrative Information Technology at the University of Michigan February 6, 1989 (Box 56)
      - Financing Information Technology February 23, 1990 (Box 56)
    - Retreat October 26, 1990 (Box 56)
    - Retreat Notes December 11, 1990 (Box 56)
    - Summary of Action Items January 1988-March 1989 (Box 56)
  - Information Technology Policy Committee/Special Committee (ITPCSPEC)
    Information Technology Policy Committee-Special Charge (ITPCSPEC) (.25 linear feet, 1981-1994). In January 1993, provost and vice president for academic affairs, Gilbert Whitaker, assigned the ITPC a special charge. The charge was to provide advice on policy in support of the University’s “electronic community.” Specific issues the committee was asked to address included the role of electronic conferencing in research and teaching; computer access to illegal materials; security and privacy of electronic communication; management policies in relationship to access and use of information technology resources at the university. Committee membership consisted of a subset of the ITPC, one student representative and three committee consultants. The series contains the key documents produced by this specially charged committee including the charge to the committee, meeting minutes, and the final report written by the committee, Policies in Support of the University’s Electronic Community.
    - Correspondence (Pollock) 1993 (Box 56)
    - Dissemination of “Electronic Community” Report 1993 (Box 56)
    - “Drafts” 1993 and not dated (Box 56)
    - Final Report
      - Policies in Support of the University’ s Electronic Community 1993 (Box 56)
    - Implementation of ITPCSPEC Recommendations September 15, 1994 (Box 56)
    - Meeting Minutes 1993 (Box 56)
    - Special Charge to Committee January 7, 1993 (Box 56)
  - Information Technology Security Education and Coordinated University Response Committee (ITSECUR)
    Information Technology Security Education and Coordinated University Response Committee (ITSECUR) (.50 linear feet, 1990-1999) comprises meeting minutes and committee working documents on a number of security and privacy issues including encryption, digital signatures and computer passwords. Draft policy and guidelines for encryption and digital signatures are contained within the series. The series also includes an aspect of information policy implementation that may not be immediately apparent and that is the educational component involved in reaching thousands of networked computer users on topics such as password security.
    - Anonymous Remailers circa 1993 (Box 56)
    - Automated Password Checking Approval 1997 (Box 56)
    - Automated Security Risk Management Tools circa 1992 (Box 56)
    - Backup and Disaster Plans Approved 1996-1997 (Box 56)
    - Charge for Information Technology Security Education and Coordinated University Response Core Team October 1994 (Box 56)
    - Committee Support Letters circa 1995 (Box 56)
    - Core Team 1994-1999, 2 folders (Box 56)
    - Early Objectives 1990-1994 (Box 57)
    - Education Plan circa 1994 (Box 57)
    - Encryption and Digital Signature
      - Guidelines 1996-1998 (Box 57)
      - Policy 1996-1997 (Box 57)
      - Subgroup 1995-1996 (Box 57)
    - Immediate Fixes Subgroup 1994-1995 (Box 57)
    - Infrastructure Working Group Report 1992 (Box 57)
    - ITSECUR Processes 1995-1996 (Box 57)
    - Managing Access to Network Jacks 1997 (Box 57)
    - Meeting Agendas and Agenda Planning 1994-1997 (Box 57)
    - Meeting Minutes
      - 1995
        - January-June, 1996 (Box 57)
        - July-December 1996 (Box 57)
        - January-June, 1997 (Box 57)
    - Models Subcommittee 1994-1995 (Box 57)
    - Personal Information Committee 1990-1995 (Box 57)
    - Project Description 1994 (Box 57)
    - Security Costs and Expenditures 1994-1996 (Box 57)
    - Security Standards Preparation 1995 (Box 57)
    - Standards Committee 1990-1996 (Box 57)
    - Unix Standards circa 1995 (Box 57)
    - User Advocate 1995-1996 (Box 57)
- Computer Sales Program 1986-1993
  The Computer Sales Program (.75 linear feet, 1986-1993) series, while slight, does show the university’s effort to fulfill the sudden demand for desktop computers on campus. This series includes a draft memorandum titled the “Background and History of the Sales Program at Michigan,” possibly written by Greg Marks. Sales of computers began at the university in the fall of 1983 when the university was invited to become one of the original members of the Apple University Consortium. By 1986, the computer sales program was selling Apple, IBM, Zenith and Wang computers. In 1986 alone over 2,000 personal computers were sold. Full-scale “computer kickoffs” were put in place by the fall of 1988. Researchers can view photographs of the 1991 kickoff in the Photographs series. Doug Van Houweling saw the future of computing technology and argued in a paper titled The Computer Sales Program at the University of Michigan, that the “sales help create the foundation and properly position the University for the pervasive, integral role of information technology in the University’s future.” This series provides material on the 1993 Internal Revenue Service audit of the computer sales program. The series also includes a memorandum (draft version) written by Baker and McKenzie re: 1989-1992 Income Tax Audit Computer Sales (Issue No. 3), December 29, 1993. The paper outlines the university’s argument for why they viewed income generated by the computer sales program as exempt from taxable income.
  - Clone Bid 1992 (Box 58)
  - Collegiate Partnership Program 1993 (Box 58)
  - Internal Revenue Service (IRS)
    - Audit 1993 (Box 58)
    - Memorandum 1989-1992 Income Tax Audit Computer Sales (Issue No. 3) December 29, 1993 (Box 58)
  - “Kickoff”
    - 1988 (Box 58)
    - 1989 (Box 58)
    - 1989 (Box 58)